<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-14T19:14:56-06:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kubeflow</title><subtitle>The Machine Learning Toolkit for Kubernetes.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Kubeflow Community Holds First Election for Kubeflow Steering Committee</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/election/2023/12/12/kubeflow-community-holds-first-election-for-kubeflow-steering-committee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kubeflow Community Holds First Election for Kubeflow Steering Committee" /><published>2023-12-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-12-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/election/2023/12/12/kubeflow-community-holds-first-election-for-kubeflow-steering-committee</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/election/2023/12/12/kubeflow-community-holds-first-election-for-kubeflow-steering-committee.html">&lt;p&gt;The Kubeflow Community, known for its dedication to making machine learning workflows on Kubernetes simple, portable, and scalable, &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss/c/54PGJ-ypqc8&quot;&gt;has recently announced&lt;/a&gt; a significant milestone in its journey. For the first time, they are holding elections for the Kubeflow Steering Committee (KSC)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KSC will be crucial in guiding the project’s direction, ensuring it continues to meet the needs of its growing user base. Candidates for this committee are drawn from the community’s diverse members, embodying the spirit of open-source collaboration that Kubeflow cherishes.
This election marks a new chapter in Kubeflow’s history, reflecting the community’s commitment to a democratic project governance model. It serves as a testament to the community’s growth, maturity, and dedication to inclusivity and shared decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The election process for the KSC is structured to ensure that every phase is transparent and fair. As per &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/blob/master/elections/kubeflow-steering-committee-elections-2023.md&quot;&gt;the announced timeline&lt;/a&gt;, we are currently in &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss/c/dEs1aGSd_X4/m/n-6pMaCnAQAJ&quot;&gt;the nomination phase&lt;/a&gt;, where &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/blob/master/elections/eligible-candidates-and-voters-2023-KSC.md&quot;&gt;eligible community members&lt;/a&gt; are encouraged to nominate themselves or others for a position on the Committee. This stage will determine the group of candidates who will move forward to the testimonial phase and then the voting phase. It’s an exciting time for the community, as members step up to the challenge and show their readiness to drive the project’s future direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections like this in the open source ecosystem highlight the collaborative spirit that drives these initiatives. They provide the opportunity for anyone, regardless of their role in the project, to step up and help guide its future. Let’s all join in congratulating the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Community&lt;/a&gt; on this milestone and look forward to the outcomes of this exciting election!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Get Involved:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are an open and welcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/&quot;&gt;community&lt;/a&gt; of software developers, data scientists, AI enthusiasts, organizations and more!  Getting involved in the Kubeflow Community is an exciting journey that offers numerous opportunities for learning, networking, and contributing to open-source development. By actively participating and sharing your ideas, you can make a meaningful impact and be part of this dynamic community. Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/#kubeflow-community-call&quot;&gt;weekly community call&lt;/a&gt;, get involved in discussions on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/#kubeflow-mailing-list&quot;&gt;the mailing list&lt;/a&gt; or chat with others on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/#kubeflow-slack&quot;&gt;Slack Workspace&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;important-dates&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Important Dates:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exceptions Phase:&lt;/strong&gt;  4 December 2023 at 0900 Pacific Time  (Starts) - 10 December 2023 at 12:00pm Pacific Time (Ends)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nomination Phase:&lt;/strong&gt; 11 December 2023 at 0900 Pacific Time  (Starts) - 24 December 2023 at 12:00pm Pacific Time (Ends)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Testimonial Phase:&lt;/strong&gt; 25 December 2023 at 0900 Pacific Time (Starts) - 7 January 2024 at 12:00pm Pacific Time (Ends)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voting Phase:&lt;/strong&gt; 8 January 2024 at 0900 Pacific Time (Starts) - 29 January 2024 at 12:00pm Pacific Time (Ends)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Announcement&lt;/strong&gt; of Election Results:  30 January 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;additional-information&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Additional Information:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/blob/master/elections/kubeflow-steering-committee-elections-2023.md&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Project Steering Committee Elections 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/blob/master/elections/eligible-candidates-and-voters-2023-KSC.md&quot;&gt;List of Eligible Voters and Candidates 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss/c/dEs1aGSd_X4/m/n-6pMaCnAQAJ&quot;&gt;[Elections] Nominations Phase - 2023 Kubeflow Project Steering Committee Elections - Opens Today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss/c/aIkzJVgsSp4/m/crpQv1EZAgAJ&quot;&gt;[Elections] 2023 Kubeflow Project Steering Committee Elections - Eligible Voters and Candidates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss/c/54PGJ-ypqc8/m/iRC2UXcvAQAJ&quot;&gt;[Elections] 2023 Kubeflow Project Steering Committee Elections - Timeline and Update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Amber Graner</name></author><category term="election" /><summary type="html">The Kubeflow Community, known for its dedication to making machine learning workflows on Kubernetes simple, portable, and scalable, has recently announced a significant milestone in its journey. For the first time, they are holding elections for the Kubeflow Steering Committee (KSC)!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kubeflow 1.8: Kubernetes MLOps delivered via Python workflows</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.8-release/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kubeflow 1.8: Kubernetes MLOps delivered via Python workflows" /><published>2023-10-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-10-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.8-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.8-release/">&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow v1.8’s powerful workflows uniquely deliver Kubernetes-native MLOps, which dramatically reduce yaml wrangling. ML pipelines are now constructed as modular components, enabling easily chainable and reusable ML workflows. The new Katib SDK reduces manual configuration and simplifies the delivery of your tuned model.  v1.8 also introduces the PVC Viewer for easier persistent storage management eliminating the need for Kubernetes CLI storage commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow 1.8 adds ARM processor support which simplifies adoption for Apple Silicon users and IoT servers. 1.8 delivers updated Tensorflow, PyTorch, Cuda notebook image examples with a detangled makefile process.  Kubeflow’s performance and security are improved via significant upgrades to the underlying components and packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;selected-and-highlighted-deliveries&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selected and Highlighted deliveries&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kubeflow-pipelines&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Pipelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow 1.8 includes KFP 2.0.3 and KFP SDK 2.4.0. The KFP Python SDK 2.4.0 release contains features present that were previewed in the v2 namespace with now full official support along with considerable additional functionality. A selection of these features include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An improved and unified Python-based authoring experience for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/pipelines/v2/components/&quot;&gt;components&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/pipelines/v2/pipelines/&quot;&gt;pipelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/pipelines/v2/pipelines/pipeline-basics/#pipelines-as-components&quot;&gt;pipelines as components&lt;/a&gt; (pipeline in pipeline)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Various additional &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/pipelines/v2/pipelines/pipeline-basics/#task-configurations&quot;&gt;configurations for tasks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compilation to an Argo-independent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/pipelines/v2/compile-a-pipeline/#ir-yaml&quot;&gt;pipeline definition&lt;/a&gt; that enables pipelines to be compiled once and run anywhere&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An improved &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/pipelines/v2/cli/&quot;&gt;KFP CLI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refreshed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/pipelines/v2/&quot;&gt;user documentation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://kubeflow-pipelines.readthedocs.io/en/sdk-2.0.0/&quot;&gt;reference documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pipeline release is focused on cross-platform portability, features such as reading and writing to a Kubernetes PVC has been moved into the extension package &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/project/kfp-kubernetes/&quot;&gt;kfp-kubernetes&lt;/a&gt;, more information can be found at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/pipelines/v2/platform-specific-features/&quot;&gt;platform specific features&lt;/a&gt; page on the Kubeflow Website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally the project &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kfp-tekton&quot;&gt;kfp-tekton&lt;/a&gt; which allows users to run pipelines with a Tekton backend, is also updated version 2.0.3 and the sdk will compile to the same pipeline spec, sdk users can use the same pipeline definition to run on both Argo and Tekton backends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;katib&quot;&gt;Katib&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The updated Katib pythonic SDK in Kubeflow v1.8 helps developers to improve model quality by simplifying the configuration and tracking of model and environmental parameters.  In this release we are happy to announce new KatibConfig API &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/2176&quot;&gt;(#2176)&lt;/a&gt; along with multiple commits improving the experience in the UI and bug fixes in the SDK.  A selection of these features and bug fixes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upgrade Tensorflow version to v2.13.0 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/2216&quot;&gt;#2216&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start waiting for certs to be ready before sending data to channel (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/2215&quot;&gt;#2215&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove a katib-webhook-cert Secret from components &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/2214&quot;&gt;(#2214&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the release can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/releases&quot;&gt;release notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-operator&quot;&gt;Training Operator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many model developers are experiencing challenges with GPU utilization, especially with large language models. The new training operator functionality provides efficient configuration, utilization and scaling for training. v1.8 improves support for gang schedulers such as volcano, scheduler-plugins and koord-schedule (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/pull/1747&quot;&gt;#1747&lt;/a&gt;).  Additionally the implementation of suspend semantics allows the external controller to delete or not create Pods depending on the state of the flag (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/pull/1859&quot;&gt;#1859&lt;/a&gt;). V1.8 also includes workflow updates and bug fixes that make model training more straightforward to use.  A selection of these features and bug fixes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make scheduler-plugins the default gang scheduler. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/pull/1747&quot;&gt;#1747&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Auto-generate RBAC manifests by the controller-gen (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/pull/1815&quot;&gt;#1815&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set correct env variables for PytorchJob to support torchrun, allowing to support different distributed training launch methods (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/pull/1840&quot;&gt;#1840&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add default Intel MPI env variables to MPIJob (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/pull/1804&quot;&gt;#1804&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fully consolidate tfjob-operator to training-operator (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/pull/1850&quot;&gt;#1850&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the release can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/releases/&quot;&gt;release notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kserve&quot;&gt;KServe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow v1.8 introduces KServe 0.11. In this release, we’ve introduced Large Language Model (LLM) runtimes, made enhancements to the KServe control plane, and updated the Python SDK with revised support for the Open Inference Protocol, as well as improved dependency management using &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/docs/&quot;&gt;poetry&lt;/a&gt;. A selection of these features and bug fixes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TorchServe 0.8.0 for LLM support (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kserve/kserve/pull/2980&quot;&gt;#2980&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implement v2/open inference endpoints for kserve python runtimes (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kserve/kserve/pull/2655&quot;&gt;2655&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding an end-to-end example for deploying a large language model on KServe (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kserve/kserve/pull/2836&quot;&gt;2836&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the KServe 0.11 release can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kserve/kserve/releases/tag/v0.11.0/&quot;&gt;release notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simplifying-storage-for-ml-workflows&quot;&gt;Simplifying Storage for ML Workflows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow’s web apps enhancements expose valuable information to data scientists, which simplifies advanced workflows.  For example, Kubernetes storage management, especially for persistent volumes, is critical for rapid data science iteration but can require complex, manual configuration.  The newly introduced PVC Viewer makes storage management easy for end users and eliminates the need to learn low-level CLI commands.    Users can click and drag to add/remove files and file directories from persistent volumes.  The volumes can easily be attached to MLOps objects, like notebooks, which makes experimenting with different data sets faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-10-23-kubeflow-1.8-release/pvc-viewer-demo.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Kubeflow user using pvc-viewer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;support-for-arm-machines&quot;&gt;Support for ARM Machines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow 1.8 brings forward a significant upgrade &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/7342&quot;&gt;(#7343)&lt;/a&gt; by officially introducing support for ARM architectures. This move ensures that developers can leverage Kubeflow’s powerful machine learning capabilities on a wider variety of devices and platforms, including the Apple Silicon and a multitude of IoT devices. This expansion highlights Kubeflow’s adaptability, ensuring seamless machine learning workflows across various hardware architectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;security---rootless-kubeflow-updates-and-fixes&quot;&gt;Security - Rootless Kubeflow Updates and Fixes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our ongoing commitment to bolstering security, version 1.8 brings both vital security fixes and innovative features. A notable endeavor by the Security Team has been the development of features that lay the groundwork for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/pull/2455&quot;&gt;rootless Kubeflow #2455&lt;/a&gt; in the future. v1.8 offers users the flexibility to run Kubeflow either with the optional istio-cni or without it. A selection of these features and bug fixes include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fix performance issue within a mysql request that could cause a denial of service (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pipelines/pull/9680&quot;&gt;#9680&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fix issue on which Profile controller and KFAM allow unauthenticated in-cluster traffic(&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/7032&quot;&gt;#7032&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding oauth2-proxy as optional alternative to oidc-authservice (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/pull/2409&quot;&gt;#2409&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future versions will continue to refine this rootless functionality, along with plans to make istio-cni the default option along with istio ambient mesh and incorporating &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/7325&quot;&gt;Pod Security Standards&lt;/a&gt;. Please join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://kubeflow.slack.com/archives/C04CF10FJ2D&quot;&gt;Security Team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notebooks&quot;&gt;Notebooks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow Notebook 1.8 brings many enhancements to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/notebooks/container-images/&quot;&gt;notebook container images&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart shows how the official images are now related to each other&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-10-23-kubeflow-1.8-release/images_diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Kubeflow notebook images&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of special note is that all notebook images (except the CUDA ones) are now built for both AMD64 and ARM64 architectures &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/7357&quot;&gt;(#7357)&lt;/a&gt;.
Additionally, it is now much easier to build custom images by running &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;make docker-build-dep&lt;/code&gt; from within the image’s folder.
We have also updated to the following package versions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Python 3.11.6&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JupyterLab 3.6.6&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tensorflow 2.13.0 and CUDA 11.8 (for Tensoflow CUDA images)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PyTorch 2.1.0 and CUDA 12.1 (for PyTorch CUDA images)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;platform-dependencies&quot;&gt;Platform dependencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow 1.8 includes hundreds of commits. The Kubeflow release process includes several rounds of testing by the Kubeflow working groups and Kubeflow distributions. Kubeflow’s configuration options provide a high degree of flexibility. After considering all of the testing options, the 1.8 Release Team narrowed the critical dependencies for consistent testing and documentation to the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Component&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://knative.dev/docs/reference/relnotes/&quot;&gt;Knative&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://istio.io/latest/news/releases/&quot;&gt;Istio&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kubernetes.io/releases/&quot;&gt;Kubernetes&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cert-manager.io/docs/installation/supported-releases/&quot;&gt;Cert-Manager&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubernetes-sigs/kustomize/releases&quot;&gt;Kustomize&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dexidp/dex/releases&quot;&gt;Dex&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/argoproj/argo-workflows/releases&quot;&gt;Argo&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tektoncd/pipeline/releases&quot;&gt;Tekton&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/arrikto/oidc-authservice&quot;&gt;Oidc&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version used in 1.8&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;1.10.2 (Serving) 1.10.1 (Eventing)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;1.17.3
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;1.25/1.26
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;1.12.2
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5.0.3
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;2.36.0
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;3.3.10
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;0.47.5
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;e236439
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The 1.8 documentation includes overall installation instructions from the Manifest Working Group, and detailed feature reviews from each Kubeflow working group. Most of the working groups have broken their changelogs into subsections that highlight core features, UI enhancements, miscellaneous updates, bug fixes and breaking changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community continues to see a large increase in activity since the announcement that Kubeflow is now part of the CNCF Incubator. The community holds regular meetings and holds elections for the Kubeflow steering committee in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 1.8 release cycle, the community continues to work in terms of security, issue triage  and documentation. Our next releases will focus on helping build components for training LLMs and scalability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-get-started-with-18&quot;&gt;How to get started with 1.8&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For trying out Kubeflow 1.8 we recommend our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/started/installing-kubeflow/&quot;&gt;installation page&lt;/a&gt; where you can choose between a selection of Kubeflow distributions. For more advanced users we also provide the manifest installation guide.   We continue to test and improve the documentation.   If you find an issue, please feel free to report and/or open a PR to help improve it for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;join-the-community&quot;&gt;Join the Community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank everyone for their contribution to Kubeflow 1.8, especially &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DnPlas&quot;&gt;Daniela Plasencia&lt;/a&gt; for his work as the v1.8 Release Manager. As you can see, the Kubeflow community is vibrant and diverse, solving real-world problems for organizations worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;want-to-help&quot;&gt;Want to help?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to help? The Kubeflow community &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/blob/master/wg-list.md&quot;&gt;Working Groups&lt;/a&gt; hold open meetings and are always looking for more volunteers and users to unlock the potential of machine learning. If you’re interested in becoming a Kubeflow contributor, please feel free to check out the resources below. We look forward to working with you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/&quot;&gt;Kubeflow website&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow&quot;&gt;Kubeflow GitHub Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://join.slack.com/t/kubeflow/shared_invite/enQtMjgyMzMxNDgyMTQ5LWUwMTIxNmZlZTk2NGU0MmFiNDE4YWJiMzFiOGNkZGZjZmRlNTExNmUwMmQ2NzMwYzk5YzQxOWQyODBlZGY2OTg&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Slack channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss&quot;&gt;kubeflow-discuss&lt;/a&gt; mailing list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attend a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/&quot;&gt;weekly community meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Kubeflow 1.8 Release Team, David Cardozo and Josh Bottum</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html">Kubeflow v1.8’s powerful workflows uniquely deliver Kubernetes-native MLOps, which dramatically reduce yaml wrangling. ML pipelines are now constructed as modular components, enabling easily chainable and reusable ML workflows. The new Katib SDK reduces manual configuration and simplifies the delivery of your tuned model. v1.8 also introduces the PVC Viewer for easier persistent storage management eliminating the need for Kubernetes CLI storage commands.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kubeflow User Survey 2023</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-user-survey-2023/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kubeflow User Survey 2023" /><published>2023-07-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-07-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-user-survey-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-user-survey-2023/">&lt;p&gt;In April 2023, the Kubeflow user survey opened, gathering community feedback. The survey aimed to comprehend the
adoption of Kubeflow and collect input on the benefits, gaps, and requirements for machine learning use cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey consisted of 21 questions, including multiple-choice and freeform formats. It ran from April 11th to May 26th
and received 90 responses. The 2023 survey yielded more targeted and actionable freeform answers, which provided further
insights into users’ requirements and potential enhancements for Kubeflow. Furthermore, we received a significant amount
of positive feedback regarding the factors that contribute to the success of Kubeflow and its community. One survey
respondent expressed their appreciation, stating, &lt;em&gt;“I love that it helps teams do high-quality ML work while providing
flexibility. I love that it is open-source. I love that the community keeps working hard and making it better.”&lt;/em&gt; Another
respondent highlighted their liking for Kubeflow due to &lt;em&gt;“the broad potential of some of the projects (like Pipelines
components) and the different integrations that make for more of an end-to-end experience.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thank everyone for participating in the survey and we will use both the improvements and positive feedback to steer
our efforts in enhancing Kubeflow, ensuring it remains a user-centric platform for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;84% of the users deploy more than one Kubeflow component&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top 3 Kubeflow components are Pipelines (90%), Notebooks (76%), and Katib (47%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top contrib component used by the user is KServe (62%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documentation (55%) is the biggest gap in Kubeflow, followed by tutorials (50%) and tied for third place,
installation (39%) and upgrades (39%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monitoring models (45%) is the biggest gap in the users’ ML lifecycle, followed by model registry (44%) and initial
setup (39%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;52% of the users use the raw manifest installation to install Kubeflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top distribution used to install Kubeflow is AWS (28%) followed by Google Cloud (17%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;74% of the users deploy Kubeflow on the cloud and 45% on-prem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;49% of the users are running Kubeflow in production&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;17% of the users are contributing back to Kubeflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;49% of the users are keeping up with the latest Kubeflow 1.7 release and 43% are running a version behind Kubeflow 1.6&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;survey-respondents&quot;&gt;Survey Respondents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-07-26-kubeflow-user-survey-2023/demographics_location_industry.png&quot; alt=&quot;2023 survey demographics and location graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kubeflow user survey drew responses from 90 members of the community mostly made up of members from the United
States (43%), Europe (34%), and Asia-Pacific (10%). The majority of the respondents were from the Tech industry (49%),
followed by Finance (13%) and Consulting (11%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is diversity in roles that make up the community, most of the community members had the title MLOps
Engineer (18%), ML Engineer (17%), and Architect (15%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last year’s 2022 User Survey, we started to see an increase in the number of users adopting Kubeflow in their
production environment and actively contributing to the Kubeflow project as their expertise with the project grew. This
year, we see the trend continuing with the highest percentage of Kubeflow running in production (49%) and the highest
number of users contributing to the project (17%). As the adoption of Kubeflow continues to rise, this will have a
significant impact on the positive growth and development of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-07-26-kubeflow-user-survey-2023/demographics_kubeflow_experience.png&quot; alt=&quot;2023 survey demographics kubeflow experience graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;documentation-and-tutorials&quot;&gt;Documentation and Tutorials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-07-26-kubeflow-user-survey-2023/kubeflow_gaps.png&quot; alt=&quot;2023 survey Kubeflow gaps graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documentation and tutorial have been a challenge in the community for a while, and the trend continues this year with
documentation (55%) voted as the number one biggest gap in Kubeflow, followed by Tutorials (49%) as the second biggest
gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous surveys, the feedback on documentation and tutorials was very generic. However, this year, the users are
asking for specific documentation to help them adopt Kubeflow better. Some of the documentation and tutorials users are
looking for are the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tutorials and examples of how to leverage the new features delivered with the new releases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An architecture diagram of Kubeflow of how each component works&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to setup Transport Layer Security (TLS) with raw manifest installation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A user onboarding documentation on how to add contributors to the platform and map credentials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documentation to show integration with other tools like MLflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examples of all the capabilities of KFP packages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documentation to cover the RBAC and authorization in Kubeflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upgrade guide for every release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the specific ask, the major themes in what type of documentation improvements users are asking for are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documentation for advanced users and advanced use cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documentation for best practices around Kubeflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More diverse end-to-end examples, not just the mnist example&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Frequent updates to documentation as many are out of date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address the challenges of Kubeflow documentation, we are looking for help from our community. If you are interested in
improving current Kubeflow documentation and work on future improvements, we invite you to join us at the next community
meeting to introduce yourself to the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;installation-and-upgrades&quot;&gt;Installation and Upgrades&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-07-26-kubeflow-user-survey-2023/kubeflow_installation.png&quot; alt=&quot;2023 survey Kubeflow installation graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the top three voted answers to the biggest gap in Kubeflow was installation tied with upgrades. The survey result
showed that 52% of the users use the raw manifest installation to install Kubeflow. With the sole support of Kustomize
as a choice of installation tool for Kubeflow, many users are looking for more diverse support for tooling, especially
Helm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest reasons for Helm support requests is due to complexity of installation. One survey respondent shared,
&lt;em&gt;“Kustomize does not quite provide the same experience and requires a lot more familiarity with the underlying systems
and manifests to properly configure…,”&lt;/em&gt; which makes installation too difficult for a small team trying to adopt
Kubeflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some, support for a different installation tool isn’t the answer. We also received much feedback on the installation
needing to be more lightweight. Due to the complexity of the stack and integration of many components, people are
struggling to customize their Kubeflow instance due to tight coupling and requirements of large resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to installation, upgrades are also on top of the mind for many of the users. While there are some upgrade
guides for specific distributions, many of the users are installing Kubeflow without distribution. Without upgrade
guides provided for the raw manifest installation, upgrades are taking a great amount of effort for the users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;monitoring-models-and-model-registry&quot;&gt;Monitoring Models and Model Registry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2023-07-26-kubeflow-user-survey-2023/kubeflow_gaps_ml_lifecycle.png&quot; alt=&quot;2023 survey Kubeflow ML lifecycle gaps graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In last year’s survey, monitoring surged to the top as the biggest gap in the machine learning lifecycle. This year, the
trend continued with monitoring (45%) voted as the number one concern, closely followed by model registry (44%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For both gaps, users are looking for a built-in solution that addresses monitoring and model registry needs, with
specific requests for support of Grafana and MLflow integrations to enable a seamless experience with Kubeflow
pipelines. With a lack of support for both of these tools, users are expressing concerns about the challenges they face
in managing and tracking their models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;security&quot;&gt;Security&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-user-survey-2022/&quot;&gt;2022 Kubeflow User Survey&lt;/a&gt;, security emerged as
one of the top three voted answers, highlighting it as a significant gap in Kubeflow. Since then, the community has
placed a strong emphasis on security, leading to the formation of the Kubeflow Security Team comprising members with a
security-focused mindset. Their primary objective is to address security concerns and ensure that Kubeflow remains a
robust and secure platform for all its users. For further details, visit
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/tree/master/security&quot;&gt;Kubeflow security team&lt;/a&gt; and consider joining the next
security team meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, all working groups are working towards the 1.8 release, planned to release
on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/tree/master/releases/release-1.8&quot;&gt;October 4th, 2023&lt;/a&gt;. Upon successful delivery
of the 1.8 release, each working group will shift their focus towards prioritizing features for the next subsequent
release. During the initial planning phase of the new release, each working group leads will reevaluate the survey
results to determine their priorities driven by your survey feedback. If you are interested in the future direction of
each working group, join them in discussing their roadmap at their future meetings. All Kubeflow community meetings can
be found in
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/#kubeflow-community-calendars&quot;&gt;Kubeflow community calendar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for improvements to the documentation and tutorials, Kubeflow community is actively seeking help from our community
members. If you are interested in improving current Kubeflow documentation and work on future improvements, we invite
you to join us at the next community meeting to introduce yourself to the community and express your interest in joining this effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-the-community&quot;&gt;Join the Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank everyone for their participation in the survey. As you can see from the survey results, the
Kubeflow Community is vibrant and diverse, solving real-world problems for organizations worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to help? The Kubeflow Community Working Groups hold open meetings and are always looking for more volunteers and
users to unlock the potential of machine learning. If you’re interested in becoming a Kubeflow contributor, check out
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/&quot;&gt;Kubeflow community page&lt;/a&gt; to learn more. We look forward to working with you!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anna Jung, Johnu George, and Josh Bottum</name></author><category term="community" /><summary type="html">In April 2023, the Kubeflow user survey opened, gathering community feedback. The survey aimed to comprehend the adoption of Kubeflow and collect input on the benefits, gaps, and requirements for machine learning use cases.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kubeflow v1.7 simplifies Kubernetes native MLOps via enhanced UI, Katib Tuning API and new training frameworks</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.7-release/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kubeflow v1.7 simplifies Kubernetes native MLOps via enhanced UI, Katib Tuning API and new training frameworks" /><published>2023-03-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-03-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.7-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.7-release/">&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow v1.7 users are capitalizing on their python knowledge to build seamless workflows without the need of Kubernetes CLI commands and without building container images for each iteration. With new UIs in multiple components, developers can correlate configuration parameters with logs which allow them to quickly analyze the results. When coupled with Kubeflow’s pythonic workflows and Kubernetes operating efficiencies, these enhancements save model developers material amounts of time and toil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release includes hundreds of new commits, and the following sections provide details on the top features. You will also find updates on platform dependencies, changelogs, breaking changes, ecosystem partners, the new Security Team and Kubeflow’s transition to the CNCF. We encourage active users to contribute to our next release, and provide links to join the community at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;selected-and-highlighted-deliveries&quot;&gt;Selected and Highlighted deliveries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;katib&quot;&gt;Katib&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katib includes new enhancements to the UI and SDK. The new Katib UI provides simplified fine-grained configuration and log correlation. Additionally sorting and filtering have been added, allowing a more organized view of your many experiments. In addition, these features minimize the necessity of manually employing low-level commands to locate and correlate logs with hyperparameter experiment configurations. This simplifies the process of in-depth performance analysis and subsequent iterations of model parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1.7, the Katib SDK provides new features including a Tune API and the ability to retreive trial metrics from the Katib database. Model developers or data scientists can execute the Tune API to start a HyperParameter Experiment without any knowledge of underlying systems e.g. Kubernetes, Docker. It automatically converts user training scripts to a Katib Experiment. The Katib changelog provides details on over 100 updates and bug fixes including these SDK and UI top features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Narrow down Katib RBAC rules (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/2091&quot;&gt;#2091&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support Postgres as a Katib DB (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/1921&quot;&gt;#1921&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[SDK] Create Tune API in the Katib SDK (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/1951&quot;&gt;#1951&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[SDK] Get Trial Metrics from Katib DB (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/2050&quot;&gt;#2050&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More Suggestion container fields in Katib Config (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/2000&quot;&gt;#2000&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Katib UI: Enable pagination/sorting/filtering (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/2017&quot;&gt;#2017&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/2040&quot;&gt;#2040&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Katib UI: Add authorization mechanisms (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/1983&quot;&gt;#1983&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;training-operator&quot;&gt;Training operator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow’s unified distributed training operator enhancements include configuration options for fine tuned resource scaling (processor, memory, storage). It now includes HPA support for Pytorch Elastic workloads where users can specify target metric/utilization in Job Spec. This is used for automatic scale up/down of Pytorch Job matching demand while ensuring the elastic policy configured by the user. These enhancements simplify user workflows significantly and reduce operational toil and costs. The Job Spec is flexible and supports multiple scheduler types: Kubernetes, volcano, custom. Major 1.7 training operator features include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PodGroup enhancements(&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/issues/1574&quot;&gt;#1574&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration with other training frameworks - Paddlepaddle(&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/issues/520&quot;&gt;#520&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhancements on Pytorch Elastic training (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/issues/1645&quot;&gt;#1645&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/issues/1626&quot;&gt;#1626&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support coscheduling plugin (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/issues/1722&quot;&gt;#1722&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[SDK] Create Unify Training Client(&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/pull/1719&quot;&gt;#1719&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pipelines&quot;&gt;Pipelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Kubeflow 1.7, the Pipelines Working Group (KFP) has continued its efforts towards KFP v2 with their latest 2.0.0-alpha.7 release. This release includes the following key enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pipelines as components: Pipelines can themselves be used as components in other pipelines, just as you would use any other single-step component in a pipeline. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pipelines/pull/8179&quot;&gt;#8179&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pipelines/pull/8204&quot;&gt;#8204&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pipelines/pull/8209&quot;&gt;#8209&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pipelines/pull/8220&quot;&gt;#8220&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sub-DAG visualization that allows pipeline users to dive deep into sub-graph components of their pipeline. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pipelines/pull/8326&quot;&gt;#8326&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Miscellaneous bug and vulnerability fixes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Model developers recognize the time-saving pythonic workflows in Kubeflow Pipelines, which speed iteration by not requiring the generation of new images for pre-prod experimentation. The new V2 UI and SDK in Kubeflow 1.7 provide valuable details on each pipeline step. This simplifies the correlation and analysis of parameters, metadata and artifacts during iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kubeflow-web-apps-notebooks-volumes-tensorboards-and-controllers&quot;&gt;Kubeflow web apps (Notebooks, Volumes, TensorBoards) and Controllers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow 1.7 delivers new web apps enhancements that expose more information to the end users and improve their UI interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A valuable new delivery is that all of the main tables have filtering &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6754&quot;&gt;#6754&lt;/a&gt; and sorting &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6742&quot;&gt;#6742&lt;/a&gt; functionalities as well as showing objects from all namespaces at once &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6778&quot;&gt;#6778&lt;/a&gt;. This allows the end users to navigate through their tools and apps (notebooks, tensorboards, volumes etc) more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, 1.7 provides an update to the Notebooks form page &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6826&quot;&gt;#6826&lt;/a&gt; as well as a dedicated page &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6769&quot;&gt;#6769&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6788&quot;&gt;#6788&lt;/a&gt; for the different types of tools managed by Kubeflow. These detailed pages allow users to view logs, events and configuration yamls and they also link from one another (i.e. going to a volume’s details page via a notebook details page). Previously these functions were only available through the Kubernetes API, which would require the user to have increased privileges and to have a more in-depth knowledge of Kubernetes CLI commands. With these new features the user has a simpler, more organized and more secure way of accessing crucial Kubeflow resource information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other notable features are small improvements on our user stories around PodDefaults. Aside from additional use-cases, like defining sidecar and init containers &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6749&quot;&gt;#6749&lt;/a&gt;, Kubeflow’s TensorBoard stack now integrates with PodDefaults &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6874&quot;&gt;#6874&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6924&quot;&gt;#6924&lt;/a&gt;. These enhancements enable the re-use of the user’s existing PodDefaults to gain S3 access from both Notebook and TensorBoard servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;platform-dependencies-breaking-changes-add-ons&quot;&gt;Platform dependencies, breaking changes, add-ons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow 1.7 includes hundreds of commits. The Kubeflow release process includes several rounds of testing by the Kubeflow working groups and Kubeflow distributions. Kubeflow’s configuration options provide a high degree of flexibility. After considering all of the testing options, the 1.7 Release Team narrowed the critical dependencies for consistent testing and documentation to the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K8s&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Istio&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KNative&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kustomize&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cert Mgr&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DEX&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Argo&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tekton&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oidc-authservice&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
 &lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.25 / 1.24
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.16
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8.1
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.2 or 5.0
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.10.1
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.31.2
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.3.8
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;e236439&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
 &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another valuable platform enhancement is the support of additional processor architectures including IBM’s Power (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/issues/6684&quot;&gt;#6684&lt;/a&gt;). This effort provides the foundation to add other processor types as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1.7 documentation includes overall &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests#kubeflow-manifests&quot;&gt;installation instructions&lt;/a&gt; from the Manifest Working Group, and detailed feature reviews from each Kubeflow working group. Most of the working groups have broken their changelogs into subsections that highlight core features, UI enhancements, miscellaneous updates, bug fixes and breaking changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working Group Changelogs including breaking changes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/releases&quot;&gt;Notebooks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md&quot;&gt;Training Operator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md&quot;&gt;Katib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pipelines/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md&quot;&gt;Pipelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kserve/kserve/releases/&quot;&gt;KServe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community has continued its work to identify core components and add-ons. Significant enhancements in add-ons include the continued integration with KServe’s v.10 release, as well as a new serving option from BentoML. The BentoML team has done a tremendous job in supporting the Kubeflow community in 1.7 and their documentation is excellent. Details on BentoML are available &lt;a href=&quot;https://modelserving.com/blog/streamline-production-ml-with-bentoml-and-kubeflow&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community continues to see a large increase in activity since the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-applied-cncf-incubating/&quot;&gt;announcement&lt;/a&gt; that Kubeflow will be donated to the CNCF by Google. The community holds regular meetings to review progress on the checklist items needed for the CNCF due diligence (&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1HXAl6ew5ZUgQaAnEHS1qEPxA5puUz2knUwXOZHU39sA/edit?userstoinvite=mchmarny@google.com&amp;amp;actionButton=1&quot;&gt;meeting notes&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 1.7 release cycle, the community formed a Security Team, which is working to improve the security profile of Kubeflow components and their dependencies. The Security Team has completed these three deliveries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set-up a github directory, slack channel and regular meeting schedule with &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/10_uYpaFWvY2NyqGBPd0dbTt1RumX8MedNcGzKSdtSOY/edit?pli=1#&quot;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Created an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/blob/v1.7-branch/docs/kf_images.txt&quot;&gt;inventory&lt;/a&gt; of container images used by Kubeflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Created a list of common vulnerabilities and errors (CVEs) in the container images.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward, the Security Team will work to develop on-going policies and to remedy security issues. For example, fixing CVEs is an on-going maintenance requirement and this function is currently provided by Kubeflow distribution providers as a value added delivery. Some distributions and end-users are working to fix CVEs in the upstream projects and the Security Team is looking for help on defining and delivering those deliveries and expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kubeflow team is working on integration efforts with the Ray and MLflow communities.The Ray integration progress has moved closer to user testing and users can find more information on this &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/pull/2383&quot;&gt;tracking issue&lt;/a&gt;. The MLflow integration is progressing and its integration is tracked &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/issues/6647&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-get-started-with-17&quot;&gt;How to get started with 1.7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For trying out Kubeflow 1.7 we recommend our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/started/installing-kubeflow/&quot;&gt;installation page&lt;/a&gt; where you can choose between a selection of Kubeflow distributions. For more advanced users we recommend the manifest &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests#installation&quot;&gt;installation guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-the-community&quot;&gt;Join the Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank everyone for their contribution to Kubeflow 1.7, especially Dominik Fleischmann for his work as the v1.7 Release Manager. As you can see, the Kubeflow community is vibrant and diverse, solving real-world problems for organizations worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to help? The Kubeflow community &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/blob/master/wg-list.md&quot;&gt;Working Groups&lt;/a&gt; hold open meetings and are always looking for more volunteers and users to unlock the potential of machine learning. If you’re interested in becoming a Kubeflow contributor, please feel free to check out the resources below. We look forward to working with you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/&quot;&gt;Kubeflow website&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow&quot;&gt;Kubeflow GitHub Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://join.slack.com/t/kubeflow/shared_invite/enQtMjgyMzMxNDgyMTQ5LWUwMTIxNmZlZTk2NGU0MmFiNDE4YWJiMzFiOGNkZGZjZmRlNTExNmUwMmQ2NzMwYzk5YzQxOWQyODBlZGY2OTg&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Slack channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss&quot;&gt;kubeflow-discuss&lt;/a&gt; mailing list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attend a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/&quot;&gt;weekly community meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Kubeflow 1.7 Release Team</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html">Kubeflow v1.7 users are capitalizing on their python knowledge to build seamless workflows without the need of Kubernetes CLI commands and without building container images for each iteration. With new UIs in multiple components, developers can correlate configuration parameters with logs which allow them to quickly analyze the results. When coupled with Kubeflow’s pythonic workflows and Kubernetes operating efficiencies, these enhancements save model developers material amounts of time and toil.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kubeflow has applied to become a CNCF incubating project</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-applied-cncf-incubating/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kubeflow has applied to become a CNCF incubating project" /><published>2022-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-applied-cncf-incubating</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-applied-cncf-incubating/">&lt;p&gt;With support from the Kubeflow Project Steering Group, Google has just &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.googleblog.com/2022/10/kubeflow-applies-to-become-a-cncf-incubating-project.html&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; the application for Kubeflow to become an incubating project in the Cloud Native Computing Foundation (CNCF).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/&quot;&gt;Kubeflow&lt;/a&gt; community are excited about how far the project has come since &lt;a href=&quot;https://kubernetes.io/blog/2017/12/introducing-kubeflow-composable/&quot;&gt;its inception&lt;/a&gt; in 2017, and are blown away by the diverse community of contributors and users we have built together. Today, Kubeflow has close to 200 contributors from over 30 organizations. Over the past five years, the project has seen almost 20,000 &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; stars, tens of thousands of commits, and hosted several user and contributor gatherings across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Kubeflow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the help of the project community, Kubeflow has developed into an end-to-end, extendable ML platform for Kubernetes, with mature components to address key stages of the ML lifecycle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;model development (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kubeflow#Kubeflow_Notebooks&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Notebooks&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;model training (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kubeflow#Kubeflow_Pipelines&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Pipelines&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kubeflow#Kubeflow_Training_Operator&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Training Operator&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;model serving (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kubeflow#KServe&quot;&gt;KServe&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;automated machine learning (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kubeflow#Katib&quot;&gt;Katib&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow’s powerful development experience helps data scientists all around the world build, train, and deploy their ML models, and gives MLOps teams the tools they need to deploy and scale advanced workflows in a variety of infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project History&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2020, with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.kubeflow.org/releases/2020/03/02/kubeflow-1-0-cloud-native-ml-for-everyone.html&quot;&gt;v1.0&lt;/a&gt; release, Kubeflow reached maturity across a core set of its stable applications. In 2022, we also graduated Kubeflow Serving as an independent project, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kserve/kserve&quot;&gt;KServe&lt;/a&gt;, which now, is incubating in &lt;a href=&quot;https://lfaidata.foundation/&quot;&gt;Linux Foundation AI &amp;amp; Data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/releases/&quot;&gt;six releases&lt;/a&gt; since v1.0 have truly been a community effort. The community, collaborating together in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/#kubeflow-working-groups&quot;&gt;16 Working Groups&lt;/a&gt;, brought to project a number of key improvements in ML workflow simplicity, resource efficiency, security, and tooling. The wider Kubeflow ecosystem has also added 10 Kubeflow distributions across multiple Cloud and on-prem environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our application for Kubeflow to become a CNCF incubating project is the next big step for the project. We’re excited to see Kubeflow get closer to its roots in the cloud-native ecosystem, and for the community to continue driving innovation in the MLOps and data science experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cncf/toc/pull/950&quot;&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt; we’ve opened today to join CNCF as an incubating project is only the first step. Google and the Kubeflow community will work with the CNCF and their Technical Oversight Committee (TOC), to meet the incubation stage requirements. While the due diligence and eventual TOC decision will take some time, the Kubeflow project will continue developing and releasing throughout this process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Kubeflow is accepted into CNCF, the project will transfer to the CNCF its source code, trademark, website, and other collaboration assets and social media accounts. As part of the donation, we will also work with the Kubeflow community to update the project governance to ensure diverse representation of the broader community. Open source comes with the responsibility to contribute, sustain, and improve the projects to make our ecosystem better. We at Google will continue to support Kubeflow and participate in the Kubeflow community as project maintainers, contributors, and users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge thank you to everyone who has contributed to Kubeflow over the years! We are excited for what lays ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Thea Lamkin, Senior Program Manager, Google, on behalf of the Kubeflow Project Steering Group&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Thea Lamkin</name></author><category term="official" /><summary type="html">With support from the Kubeflow Project Steering Group, Google has just announced the application for Kubeflow to become an incubating project in the Cloud Native Computing Foundation (CNCF).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kubeflow v1.6 delivers support for Kubernetes v1.22 and introduces an alpha release of the Kubeflow Pipeline v2 functionality</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.6-release/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kubeflow v1.6 delivers support for Kubernetes v1.22 and introduces an alpha release of the Kubeflow Pipeline v2 functionality" /><published>2022-08-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-08-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.6-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.6-release/">&lt;p&gt;The Kubeflow Community is excited to announce the availability of the Kubeflow v1.6 software release, which includes
 support for Kubernetes v1.22 and introduces an alpha release of the Kubeflow Pipeline v2 (KFP v2) functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow v1.6 also adds new hyperparameter support for the population based algorithm in Katib, and provides a combined
 Python SDK for PyTorch, MXNet, MPI, XGBoost in Kubeflow’s distributed Training Operator. For model serving, v1.6 has
 new ClusterServingRuntime and ServingRuntime CRDs, and a new Model Spec was introduced to the InferenceService
 Predictor Spec, which provides a new way to specify models in KServe 0.8. Additionally, v1.6 cleans up a few CVEs in
 the central dashboard and enables the PodDefaults webhook to pick-up new certificate updates.   For the Kubernetes upgrade,
 the community developed and tested each Kubeflow component manifest with Kubernetes v1.22.  As v1.22 introduced some breaking changes, the upgrade was a team effort, and this Kubeflow release management process will be useful in the community’s future updates of Kubernetes and other software dependencies. The software is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/releases/tag/v1.6.0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel to developing these new software features, the Kubeflow Community also completed its annual user survey.
 The survey generated many good user insights into requirements for Kubeflow, and you can see more on the
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/blog/pull/121&quot;&gt;survey results&lt;/a&gt;. Of the many
 highlights, we would like to identify the growing request for model monitoring as shown in the chart below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2022-08-24-kubeflow-1.6-release/2022-user-survey-gaps-in-ml-activities-and-workflow.png&quot; alt=&quot;2022 User Survey Gaps In ML Activities and Workflow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe the increased focus on monitoring identifies Kubeflow’s maturing user base. The Community is making efforts
 to explain Kubeflow’s current functionality and build into the users’ new model monitoring requirements. In addition,
 the user survey results and Kubeflow Working Group roadmaps will be discussed in the upcoming Kubeflow Summit. You can
 learn more about the Kubeflow Summit &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1fLg1EqVtJekcXxT8GM_Rqg0-G-vIDVCrzuxE06Oq9dI/edit&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To round back to the current software delivery, the following takes a deeper look at the v1.6 highlights in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;kubeflow-v16-details&quot;&gt;Kubeflow v1.6 details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a new feature introduction standpoint, Kubeflow v1.6 includes an experimental release of the KFP v2’s new front-end,
 back-end and SDK, which deliver a modern UI and DAG, first class support for metadata, and a simplified component
 authoring experience. This slide deck, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1HzMwtI2QN67xQp2lSxmuXhitEsukLB7mvZx4KAPub3A/edit#slide=id.gecbd775238_0_20&quot;&gt;KFP v2 Introduction&lt;/a&gt;,
 provides a good overview of v2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KFP v2 alpha introduces:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An Argo-agnostic approach for creating and running pipelines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A brand new DAG visualization, which uses the Pipeline Template and MLMD in this &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pipelines/blob/master/api/v2alpha1/pipeline_spec.proto&quot;&gt;pipeline spec&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1HzMwtI2QN67xQp2lSxmuXhitEsukLB7mvZx4KAPub3A/edit#slide=id.gecbd775238_0_438&quot;&gt;Streamlined Component Authoring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can learn more about KFP v2 and the related breaking changes in these docs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1HzMwtI2QN67xQp2lSxmuXhitEsukLB7mvZx4KAPub3A/edit#slide=id.gb4a3fac3a8_7_1911&quot;&gt;KFP v2 Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kubeflow-pipelines.readthedocs.io/en/master/&quot;&gt;The SDK reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1nCUUVRXexXbQ0LDkGHsMIBDSu1WvJA9Upy1JzybNVMk/edit&quot;&gt;Breaking changes&lt;/a&gt; including an SDK change from &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kfp.v2&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;kfp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those users who are still relying on the KFP v1 functionality, Kubeflow v1.6 and its KFP v2 component are fully
 tested and supported with the mature features in the legacy Kubeflow Pipelines v1.8 SDK. This provides the same
 functionality that thousands of KFP v1 users leverage in production today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the KFP v2 alpha, Kubeflow 1.6 includes feature enhancements and operational improvements for Katib
 users. These include support for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The population based training algorithm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhanced validation checks for configurations, which will save time debugging parameter misconfiguration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security fixes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MetricsUnavailable Status support, which will make debugging easier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Kubeflow v1.6, the Training Operator Working Group added these valuable enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Python SDK for PyTorch, MXNet, MPI, XGBoost&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Clientset (Golang) is also generated for PyTorch, MXNet, MPI, XGBoost&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gang scheduling support for MPI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow v1.6 has several functional and operational improvements to Kubeflow notebooks, central dashboard, webapps and
 controllers. The following highlights the closed PRs that were considered medium-sized or larger. You can review
 the full list of the closed PRs &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pulls?page=1&amp;amp;q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/issues/6353&quot;&gt;Support for K8s 1.22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/issues/5560&quot;&gt;PodDefaults webhook picking up new certificates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show objects from all names spaces in Central Dashboard, Jupyter, Tensorboard, Volumes Mgr&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Updated the hosting container registry of images, note - this could be a breaking change for users with custom manifests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/pull/6519&quot;&gt;CVE fixes for Central Dashboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Manifest Working Group contributed several enhancements in 1.6. These enhancements include the testing of each
 Kubeflow’s component manifest for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/pull/2230&quot;&gt;Compatibility with K8s 1.22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/pull/2230&quot;&gt;The manifests that can be applied&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/pull/2230&quot;&gt;The Pods of components that can become ready&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/pull/2249&quot;&gt;The basic objects that can be created&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For model serving, Kubeflow v1.6 incorporates the KServe v0.8.0 release, which includes these enhancements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ClusterServingRuntime and ServingRuntime CRDs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new Model Spec is introduced to the InferenceService Predictor Spec as a new way to specify models&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for Knative 1.0+&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gRPC for transformer to predictor network communication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multi-namespace support for the ModelMesh alternative backend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KServe has these breaking changes to the Python SDK:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KFModel is renamed to Model&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KFServer is renamed to ModelServer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KFModelRepository is renamed to ModelRepository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more please see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kserve/kserve/releases/tag/v0.8.0&quot;&gt;KServe v0.8 release notes&lt;/a&gt; and
 Release &lt;a href=&quot;https://kserve.github.io/website/0.9/blog/articles/2022-02-18-KServe-0.8-release/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-the-community&quot;&gt;Join the community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank everyone for their contribution to Kubeflow 1.6, especially Anna Jung for her work as the v1.6 Release Manager. The Kubeflow community is incredibly pleased
 to have Amazon Web Services extending their support by offering &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/awscredits/&quot;&gt;AWS promotional credits&lt;/a&gt;.
 We hope this sponsorship will enable many Kubeflow Working groups to sustainably host their testing and CI/CD
 infrastructure on AWS, which is essential for maintaining the community’s high development velocity. As you can see,
 the Kubeflow community is vibrant and diverse, solving real-world problems for organizations worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to help? The Kubeflow community &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/blob/master/wg-list.md&quot;&gt;Working Group&lt;/a&gt; hold
 open meetings and are always looking for more volunteers and users to unlock the potential of machine learning. If
 you’re interested in becoming a Kubeflow contributor, please feel free to check out the resources below. We look
 forward to working with you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/&quot;&gt;Kubeflow website&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow&quot;&gt;Kubeflow GitHub Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://join.slack.com/t/kubeflow/shared_invite/enQtMjgyMzMxNDgyMTQ5LWUwMTIxNmZlZTk2NGU0MmFiNDE4YWJiMzFiOGNkZGZjZmRlNTExNmUwMmQ2NzMwYzk5YzQxOWQyODBlZGY2OTg&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Slack channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss&quot;&gt;kubeflow-discuss&lt;/a&gt; mailing list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attend a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/&quot;&gt;weekly community meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Kubeflow 1.6 Release Team</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html">The Kubeflow Community is excited to announce the availability of the Kubeflow v1.6 software release, which includes support for Kubernetes v1.22 and introduces an alpha release of the Kubeflow Pipeline v2 (KFP v2) functionality.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kubeflow User Survey 2022</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-user-survey-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kubeflow User Survey 2022" /><published>2022-08-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-08-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-user-survey-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-user-survey-2022/">&lt;p&gt;In May 2022, the Kubeflow user survey was opened to gather community feedback. The goal of the survey was to understand the adoption of Kubeflow and to gather input on the benefits, gaps, and requirements for machine learning use cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey was comprised of 24 questions (multiple choice and freeform). It ran from May 6th to June 7th and received 151 responses. Out of the 151 responses, 91 responses provided optional feedback on how to improve Kubeflow and the Community. In the 2022 survey, we received an increased number of freeform answers, which provided additional insights into users’ needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;85% of the users deploy more than one Kubeflow component&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top 3 Kubeflow components are Pipelines (89%), Notebooks (75%), KServe (Formally KFServing) (63% - the combined result of distinct users using KServe or KFServing or both).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data preprocessing and transformations are the most challenging (44%) and time-consuming (73%) steps in the ML lifecycle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;59% of the users identify model monitoring as the biggest gap in their ML lifecycle and 32% of the users identify model monitoring as the most challenging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;44% of the users are running Kubeflow in production&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;90% of the users rely on the Kubeflow community for the latest tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The top 5 ML tools used by the Kubeflow users are Tensorflow (66%), Scikit-Learn (61%), PyTorch (60%), Keras (44%), and MLflow (43%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;47% of the users are keeping up with the latest Kubeflow 1.5 release, and 42% are running Kubeflow 1.4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of documentation and tutorials are the biggest challenges in Kubeflow adoption&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Installation and upgrading of Kubeflow are a challenge for the users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users like to see security issues, especially CVEs in images addressed promptly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Namespace isolation is the top feature request from the community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;survey-respondents&quot;&gt;Survey Respondents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kubeflow user survey drew responses from 151 members of the community with experience running Kubeflow in production (44%), in the lab (23%), have experience upgrading Kubeflow cluster (18%), contributing to Kubeflow (10%), and just starting (5%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the respondents were from the Tech industry (48%), followed by Finance (15%) and Healthcare (8%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top job titles were ML Engineers (47%), Architect (26%), and Data Scientist / Analyst (23%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2022-08-19-kubeflow-user-survey-2022/demographics-industry.png&quot; alt=&quot;2022 survey demographics industry graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2022-08-19-kubeflow-user-survey-2022/demographics-title.png&quot; alt=&quot;2022 survey demographics title graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;documentation-and-tutorials&quot;&gt;Documentation and Tutorials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of documentation and tutorials are the biggest challenges in Kubeflow adoption. With new features and releases of components, the community is seeking better examples and tutorials that would help them adopt the new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, many are still finding Kubeflow to be complicated. Users asked for additional clarity on the inner workings of Kubeflow and how to integrate with many other ML components, including other Kubeflow components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few of the requests from the community include&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Up-to-date versioned documentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A hosted playground platform to demo and learn features of Kubeflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Comparison between Kubeflow and other ML tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tips and knowledge around running Kubeflow in production&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;End-to-end tutorials on how to get the most out of all components that make up Kubeflow release&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better example documentation from Kubeflow distributions owners&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Q&amp;amp;A Forum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2022-08-19-kubeflow-user-survey-2022/documentation-word-cloud.png&quot; alt=&quot;2022 survey documentation word cloud&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;installation-and-upgrades&quot;&gt;Installation and Upgrades&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the top three voted answers to the biggest gap in Kubeflow was installation (tied with security). In addition, &amp;gt; 25% of the freeform answers mentioned feedback about the installation process and/or installation tools that users would like to see supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users are looking for easier installation with better support to upgrade their Kubeflow components and cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;security&quot;&gt;Security&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“… with the current state of Kubeflow, none of our customers is able to use Kubeflow without extensive modifications, as there are widely gaping security issues and tons of CVEs across all images that need to be patched before going anywhere near production.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the top three voted answers to the biggest gap in Kubeflow was security (tied with installation). In addition, 16% of the freeform answers mentioned the need to improve security in Kubeflow, with top concerns being CVEs in images and user isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2022-08-19-kubeflow-user-survey-2022/kubeflow-gaps.png&quot; alt=&quot;2022 survey biggest gaps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kubernetes-versions&quot;&gt;Kubernetes Versions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Follow k8s release cycles ahead of time, there must be support for the latest k8s versions before the oldest get officially EOL’d. Note also major changes in 1.25!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The community raised valid concerns about Kubeflow’s lack of support for the latest Kubernetes versions. With Kubernetes 1.21 reaching its end of life on June 28th, 2022, the users found the lack of 1.22 support in the 1.5 release problematic and requested Kubeflow to keep up with the release of its dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;namespace-isolation&quot;&gt;Namespace Isolation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 15% of the free-from responses contained the word “namespace” in relation to resource isolation that users like to see supported by Kubeflow. Many users are seeking namespaced isolation across various Kubeflow resources, which include pipelines, experiments, artifacts, and metadata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From all the list of features requested in the survey, namespace isolation is the top request from the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparison-to-2021-user-survey&quot;&gt;Comparison to 2021 User Survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;challenges-with-monitoring&quot;&gt;Challenges with Monitoring&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both 2021 and 2022, Kubeflow users identified that data preprocessing and transformation are the most time-consuming and challenging steps in the machine learning lifecycle. While the top answers stayed the same, there were big changes to the follow-up rankings for the most challenging question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021, the top 5 challenges were data preprocessing and transformation, pipeline building, feature engineering, hyperparameter tuning, and distributed training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2022, the top 5 challenges were data preprocessing and transformation, feature engineering, model monitoring, distributed training, and pipeline building. The biggest difference from last year is the change in ranking for hyperparameter tuning and seeing model monitoring moving up in the ranks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/2022-08-19-kubeflow-user-survey-2022/ml-task-time-consuming-challenging.png&quot; alt=&quot;2022 survey - ML tasks time consuming and challenging&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;2022&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-03-11-survey/image8.png&quot; alt=&quot;2021 survey - ML tasks time consuming and challenging&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;2021&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As users find model monitoring one of the challenges in the machine learning lifecycle, it has also been identified as the biggest gap in users’ ML activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2021, the biggest gap was identified as connecting data pipelines to ML pipelines. In 2022, the biggest gap was identified as model monitoring. While the top three answers haven’t changed, data shows that monitoring is at the top of the mind of users as they find it to be most challenging and where the biggest gaps exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/2022-08-19-kubeflow-user-survey-2022/gaps-in-ml-activities-and-workflow.png&quot; alt=&quot;2022 survey - gaps in ML activities and workflow&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;2022&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/2021-03-11-survey/image9.png&quot; alt=&quot;2021 survey - gaps in ML activities and workflow&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;2021&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;full-survey-results&quot;&gt;Full Survey Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full survey results can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/u/2/g/kubeflow-discuss/c/UXNmOWNmu1k&quot;&gt;initial survey results&lt;/a&gt; and in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TKI-KR4oopm0G6oIMwUUJ_z6ox5BE6fnjSbEUoisnLE/edit#heading=h.e8zqwmv6lumd&quot;&gt;summary of the free-from answers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey results will be discussed with the Kubeflow community during the Kubeflow summit in October. More details about the summit will be shared via the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss&quot;&gt;kubeflow-discuss&lt;/a&gt; mailing list. Join the mailing list to keep up to date with Kubeflow summit news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-the-community&quot;&gt;Join the Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank everyone for their participation in the survey. As you can see from the survey results, the Kubeflow Community is vibrant and diverse, solving real-world problems for organizations worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to help? The Kubeflow Community Working Groups hold open meetings and are always looking for more volunteers and users to unlock the potential of machine learning. If you’re interested in becoming a Kubeflow contributor, please feel free to check out the resources below. We look forward to working with you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/&quot;&gt;Kubeflow website&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow&quot;&gt;Kubeflow GitHub Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://join.slack.com/t/kubeflow/shared_invite/enQtMjgyMzMxNDgyMTQ5LWUwMTIxNmZlZTk2NGU0MmFiNDE4YWJiMzFiOGNkZGZjZmRlNTExNmUwMmQ2NzMwYzk5YzQxOWQyODBlZGY2OTg&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Slack&lt;/a&gt; workspace&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/g/kubeflow-discuss&quot;&gt;kubeflow-discuss&lt;/a&gt; mailing list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attend a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/&quot;&gt;weekly community meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Kubeflow 1.6 Release Team</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html">In May 2022, the Kubeflow user survey was opened to gather community feedback. The goal of the survey was to understand the adoption of Kubeflow and to gather input on the benefits, gaps, and requirements for machine learning use cases.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kubeflow 1.5.1 Release Announcement</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.5.1-release/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kubeflow 1.5.1 Release Announcement" /><published>2022-07-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-07-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.5.1-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.5.1-release/">&lt;p&gt;The Kubeflow Community is excited to announce the release of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/releases/tag/v1.5.1&quot;&gt;Kubeflow 1.5.1&lt;/a&gt;. The Kubeflow 1.5.1 release provides a valuable enhancement to the caching feature of Kubeflow Pipeline (KFP) for any Kubernetes distribution with strict security policies for user application certificates. Caching is one of the crucial features of KFP which enables skipping a step that has already been executed which saves time and money. This release unblocks the caching feature to be used on distributions like AWS, the Mercedes Benz cluster, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow 1.5.1 includes the enhancements for the Kubeflow Pipelines cache server and the cert generation mechanism &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/issues/2165&quot;&gt;#2165&lt;/a&gt;. These enhancements improve the operations of Kubernetes clusters with strict security policies, especially in clusters where non-Kubelet applications cannot create API server type certificates. Kubeflow Pipelines introduced dependency on cert-manager for this enhancement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of Kubeflow distribution providers are supporting Kubeflow 1.5.1. These cloud provider and vendor distributions include additional enhancements and professional support, which many users find valuable. Please find a list of the Kubeflow distribution providers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/started/installing-kubeflow/#install-a-packaged-kubeflow-distribution&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Kartik Kalamadi, Suraj Kota, Kimonas Sotirchos and James Liu for driving this effort!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kubeflow 1.5 Release Team</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html">The Kubeflow Community is excited to announce the release of Kubeflow 1.5.1. The Kubeflow 1.5.1 release provides a valuable enhancement to the caching feature of Kubeflow Pipeline (KFP) for any Kubernetes distribution with strict security policies for user application certificates. Caching is one of the crucial features of KFP which enables skipping a step that has already been executed which saves time and money. This release unblocks the caching feature to be used on distributions like AWS, the Mercedes Benz cluster, etc.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kubeflow v1.5 improves ML model accuracy, reduces infrastructure costs and optimizes MLOps</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.5-release/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kubeflow v1.5 improves ML model accuracy, reduces infrastructure costs and optimizes MLOps" /><published>2022-04-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-04-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.5-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/kubeflow-1.5-release/">&lt;p&gt;The Kubeflow v1.5 software release improves ML model accuracy, lowers infrastructure costs, and simplifies operations by providing a more consistent user experience between components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lower-infrastructure-costs-and-improve-model-accuracy&quot;&gt;Lower infrastructure costs and improve model accuracy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several enhancements in Kubeflow v1.5 lower infrastructure costs and help improve model accuracy.  For example, new elastic training augments the Kubeflow training operator for PyTorch and enables PyTorch workers to be scaled up and down, providing fault tolerant and elastic training. This allows the training jobs to continue without restarting from scratch even if a worker fails. Elastic training can also enable the use of ephemeral or spot instances, which can save infrastructure costs. See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/blob/b56452405e44c05ed60145a19bb86be55f3833d5/proposals/pytorch-elastic-proposal.md&quot;&gt;elastic training proposal&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, v1.5 extends notebook monitoring and culling. Kernel monitoring shuts down notebook servers that have been inactive when a configurable timer expires. Kubeflow v1.5 introduces greater precision in assessing notebook server UI activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, v1.5 includes &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/1709&quot;&gt;early validation of hyperparameter tuning&lt;/a&gt;.  This feature improves model accuracy by reducing the overfitting of the model to the data sets used during hyperparameter tuning.  It can also reduce the infrastructure used as it will stop hyperparameter tuning when configurable thresholds are reached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simplified-operations&quot;&gt;Simplified operations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;v1.5 simplifies operations in several ways including easier support of high availability for the Katib Controller via the new hyperparameter leader &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/katib/pull/1713&quot;&gt;election&lt;/a&gt;.  v1.5 also adds the MPI framework to the Unified Training Operator, which deploys a single operator for handling the most popular frameworks: Tensorflow, Pytorch, MXNet, XGBoost and MPI.  Kubeflow Pipelines (KFP) has incorporated support for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/components/pipelines/installation/choose-executor/#emissary-executor&quot;&gt;Emissary Executor&lt;/a&gt; as the default executor, which means that users are not required to manually configure this option to Emissary.  This enhancement also enables KFP to support the newer Kubernetes versions that require a Container Runtime Interface (CRI) and provides support for Docker containers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, KServe v0.7 is integrated with Kubeflow v1.5.  For users who are still using KFServing v0.6.1, v1.5 does support the installation of the KFServing v0.6.1 release.  For users migrating from KFServing to KServe, there is helpful documentation, which you can find &lt;a href=&quot;https://kserve.github.io/website/0.7/admin/migration/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  From a feature standpoint, KServe v0.7 has added a beta of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kserve/modelmesh-serving&quot;&gt;ModelMesh&lt;/a&gt;, which enables easier scaling of model serving and provides an architecture that overcomes pod and IP limitations that limit the number of models that can run on a single node and/or cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note on K8s 1.22: Although many of the Kubeflow services (KFP, AutoML, Training Operator, KServe) have started testing with K8s 1.22, v1.5 was not thoroughly tested with K8s 1.22.   Additionally, critical work is still outstanding for Kubeflow Notebooks and other central services.  While the Community always encourages testing, K8s 1.22 is not formally supported with Kubeflow v1.5.  K8s 1.22 support is on the roadmap for Kubeflow’s next release and if you are interested in K8s 1.22 support, please add a comment on this tracking &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/kubeflow/issues/6098&quot;&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;streamlined-user-experience&quot;&gt;Streamlined user experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In v1.5, the Kubeflow User Interface (UI) dashboards for Notebooks, Tensorboards and Volume Manager more closely match KFP’s dashboard.   These enhancements include how dashboard fields are displayed and how operations are performed.  This gives users a consistent look and feel when working in the UI. Additionally, the Kubeflow notebooks manager web app form and its configuration template have been updated for allowing users to fully define the PVC objects that will be created for a notebook. This will give end users the ability to modify crucial parts of the PVCs, such as StorageClasses, and to more easily support popular storage offerings, including NFS. In addition, AutoML has also updated its SDK, CI framework and parameter settings across frameworks (goptuna, optuna, hyperopt).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;installation-tutorials-and-documentation&quot;&gt;Installation, tutorials and documentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kubeflow v1.5 release process includes improvements to Kubeflow’s installation, tutorial and documentation.  For installation, the Manifest Working Group’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; provided the starting place for the Kubeflow &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/started/installing-kubeflow/&quot;&gt;distributions&lt;/a&gt;, and this collaboration has increased the maturity of the code and documentation for Kubeflow’s GitOps installation pattern.  The v1.5 release process included a tracking &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/website/issues/3130&quot;&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt; for the critical web pages that are updated in each release.  Additionally, there are many Working Group documentation updates and we invite you to open issues when you find documentation that needs improvement.  Kubeflow v1.5 also includes two tutorials, which are described below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutorial 1&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pipelines/blob/master/samples/contrib/kubeflow-e2e-mnist/kubeflow-e2e-mnist.ipynb&quot;&gt;E2E MNIST with Kubeflow Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;,which provides an end-to-end test sequence i.e. start a notebook, run a pipeline, execute training, hyperparameter tuning and model serving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutorial 2&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/external-add-ons/kserve/first_isvc_kserve/&quot;&gt;Deploy and run your first interfere service with KServe Tutorial&lt;/a&gt; Run your first interface service on Kubeflow 1.5 i.e. define, create and check an InferenceService, post an interfere request and receive response.  Optionally run performance tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-the-community&quot;&gt;Join the community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The v1.5 Release Team would like to thank everyone for their efforts on Kubeflow v1.5, especially the users, code contributors, working group leads, and distribution team leads. As you can see from the extensive contributions to Kubeflow 1.5, the Kubeflow Community is vibrant and diverse, and solving real world problems for organizations around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excited to contribute your great ideas? The Kubeflow Community &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/blob/master/wg-list.md&quot;&gt;Working Groups&lt;/a&gt; hold open meetings, public lists, and are always looking for more volunteers and users to unlock the potential of machine learning. If you’re interested in becoming a Kubeflow contributor, please feel free to check out the resources below. We look forward to working with you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/&quot;&gt;Kubeflow website&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Github page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://join.slack.com/t/kubeflow/shared_invite/enQtMjgyMzMxNDgyMTQ5LWUwMTIxNmZlZTk2NGU0MmFiNDE4YWJiMzFiOGNkZGZjZmRlNTExNmUwMmQ2NzMwYzk5YzQxOWQyODBlZGY2OTg&quot;&gt;Kubeflow Slack Channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/kubeflow-discuss&quot;&gt;kubeflow-discuss&lt;/a&gt; mailing list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attend a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kubeflow.org/docs/about/community/&quot;&gt;weekly community meeting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Kubeflow 1.5 Release Team</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html">The Kubeflow v1.5 software release improves ML model accuracy, lowers infrastructure costs, and simplifies operations by providing a more consistent user experience between components.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://blog.kubeflow.org/images/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unified Training Operator release announcement</title><link href="https://blog.kubeflow.org/unified-training-operator-1.3-release/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unified Training Operator release announcement" /><published>2021-10-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-10-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.kubeflow.org/unified-training-operator-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.kubeflow.org/unified-training-operator-1.3-release/">&lt;p&gt;The Kubeflow Training Operator Working Group introduced several enhancements in the recent Kubeflow 1.4 release. The most significant was the introduction of the new unified &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator&quot;&gt;training operator&lt;/a&gt; that enables Kubernetes custom resources (CR) for many of the popular training frameworks: Tensorflow, Pytorch, MXNet and XGboost. In addition, the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tf-operator&lt;/code&gt; repository has been renamed to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;training-operator&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This single operator provides several valuable benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better resource utilisation&lt;/strong&gt; - For  releases prior to 1.4, each framework had a separate corresponding controller managing its distributed job. The unified training operator manages all distributed jobs across frameworks, which improves resource utilization and performance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less maintenance overhead&lt;/strong&gt; - Unified training operator reduces the maintenance efforts in managing distributed jobs across the framework. By default, all supported schemas(TFJob, PyTorchJob, MXNetJob, XGBoostJob) are enabled. However, specific schemas can be enabled using the flag ‘enable-scheme’. Setting this flag enables the user to enable the framework(s) that are necessary for the deployment environment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easy adoption of new operators&lt;/strong&gt; - Common code is abstracted from all framework implementations, which makes it easy for adopting new operators with less code. The common infrastructure &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/common&quot;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; can be reused for many of the new operator efforts. Reference: Paddle operator &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/pull/502&quot;&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt;, DGL operator &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/pull/512&quot;&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better developer experience&lt;/strong&gt; - Common features can be shared across frameworks without code duplication thereby, creating a developer friendly environment. For example, Prometheus Monitoring and Job Scheduling features are common, making them available to all frameworks without any extra code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unified training operator’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/tree/v1.4-branch/apps/training-operator/upstream&quot;&gt;manifests&lt;/a&gt; include an enhanced training operator, which manages custom resource definitions for TFJob, PyTorchJob, MXNet Job and  XGBoostJob. All individual operator repositories, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pytorch-operator&quot;&gt;pytorch-operator&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mxnet-operator&quot;&gt;mxnet-operator&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/xgboost-operator&quot;&gt;xgboost-operator&lt;/a&gt;, will be archived soon. Please check out the latest &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/releases/tag/v1.3.0&quot;&gt;release&lt;/a&gt; for more details and give it a try!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;release-highlights&quot;&gt;Release highlights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kubeflow 1.4 release includes the following major changes to training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;universal-training-operator-changes&quot;&gt;Universal Training Operator changes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unified Training Operator for TF, PyTorch, MXNet, XGBoost &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1302&quot;&gt;#1302&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1295&quot;&gt;#1295&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1294&quot;&gt;#1294&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1293&quot;&gt;#1293&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1296&quot;&gt;#1296&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More common code refactoring for reusability &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1297&quot;&gt;#1297&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API code restructuring to consistent format &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1300&quot;&gt;#1300&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prometheus counters for all frameworks &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1375&quot;&gt;#1375&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Python SDK for all frameworks &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1420&quot;&gt;#1420&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API doc for all frameworks &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1370&quot;&gt;#1370&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restructuring of examples across all frameworks &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1373&quot;&gt;#1373&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/tf-operator/pull/1391&quot;&gt;#1391&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;common-package-updates&quot;&gt;Common package updates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make training container port customizable to support profiling &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/common/pull/131&quot;&gt;#131&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optimize the TTL setting of all Jobs &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/common/pull/137&quot;&gt;#137&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More appropriate use of expectation for Jobs &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/common/pull/139&quot;&gt;#139&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mpi-operator-updates&quot;&gt;MPI Operator updates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scalability improvements to reduce pressure on kube-apiserver &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mpi-operator/pull/360&quot;&gt;#360&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;V2beta1 MPIJob API &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mpi-operator/pull/366&quot;&gt;#366&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mpi-operator/pull/378&quot;&gt;#378&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intel MPI Support &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mpi-operator/pull/389&quot;&gt;#389&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mpi-operator/pull/403&quot;&gt;#403&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mpi-operator/pull/417&quot;&gt;#417&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mpi-operator/pull/425&quot;&gt;#425&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mpi-operator-roadmap&quot;&gt;MPI Operator roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MPI framework integration with the unified training operator is under development and is planned for delivery in the next release i.e. post 1.4. Currently, it needs to be separately installed using MPIJob &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/manifests/tree/v1.4-branch/apps/mpi-job/upstream&quot;&gt;manifests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unified training operator is the outcome of efforts from all existing Kubeflow training operators and aims to provide a unified and simplified experience for both users and developers. We’d like to thank everyone who has contributed to and maintained the original operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PyTorch Operator: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pytorch-operator/graphs/contributors&quot;&gt;list of contributors&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/pytorch-operator/blob/master/OWNERS&quot;&gt;maintainers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MPI Operator: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mpi-operator/graphs/contributors&quot;&gt;list of contributors&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mpi-operator/blob/master/OWNERS&quot;&gt;maintainers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;XGBoost Operator: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/xgboost-operator/graphs/contributors&quot;&gt;list of contributors&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/xgboost-operator/blob/master/OWNERS&quot;&gt;maintainers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MXNet Operator: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mxnet-operator/graphs/contributors&quot;&gt;list of contributors&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/mxnet-operator/blob/master/OWNERS&quot;&gt;maintainers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-the-wg-training&quot;&gt;Join the WG-Training&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to help, or are looking for issues to work on, feel free to check the resources below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slack: &lt;a href=&quot;https://kubeflow.slack.com/archives/C018N3M6QKB&quot;&gt;#wg-training&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/kubeflow/community/tree/master/wg-training&quot;&gt;wg-training&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issues: https://github.com/kubeflow/training-operator/issues&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Johnu George, Jiaxin Shan, Josh Bottum</name></author><category term="release" /><summary type="html">The Kubeflow Training Operator Working Group introduced several enhancements in the recent Kubeflow 1.4 release. The most significant was the introduction of the new unified training operator that enables Kubernetes custom resources (CR) for many of the popular training frameworks: Tensorflow, Pytorch, MXNet and XGboost. In addition, the tf-operator repository has been renamed to training-operator.</summary></entry></feed>